How do we accomplish what needs to get done
when an easier or more appealing option exists?
For example why don't we always sleep in,
binge watch tv, or leave work early?
The answer comes down to motivation.
Motivation is what inspires us to act
and it comes from many sources.
There are three primary types of motivators.
First we might be motivated by a sense of obligation,
such as when we attend a party we'd rather not go to.
Or we might be inspired by extrinsic motivators
that come from outside.
We push ahead because we expect a reward or recognition.
And finally we might be motivated by intrinsic factors
that come from within.
Self-motivation is intrinsic.
We work towards personal results
rather than external rewards.
With self-motivation you can use your emotions
as drivers to push you toward your goals
and remain resilient.
Of all the motivators it's the most stable
since it's something that only you can control.
No one else can give it or take it away.
So let's take a look at some of the personal
and leadership benefits of self-motivation
as well as how you can improve the skills.
The first benefit of self-motivation
is that it's associated with an achievement drive.
You're driven to create challenging goals
and work towards those objectives.
And as a leader that helps you set
a standard of excellence, avoid complacency,
and inspire your staff with future-focused vision.
Second, with high self-motivation you're also likely
to have a high sense of commitment and follow through.
You're willing to make sacrifices for your goals
and that helps you earn a team confidence.
Third, with self-motivation you're also more likely
to take the initiative.
So rather than waiting for opportunities to come to you,
you'll proactively seek them out.
And as a leader, that mentality can help you take charge
and push your team to action.
And finally self-motivation cultivates optimism.
Rather than giving up when faced with setbacks,
you persevere and work through obstacles
and that can inspire others to adopt the same mindset
and push past their own temporary hiccups.
There are several strategies you can follow
to increase your self-motivation.
Here are five well known techniques.
The first strategy for increasing your self-motivation
is to define your why's.
If you can't remember why you're making sacrifices,
then it's difficult to keep going.
So spend sometime thinking about what inspires you.
Consider your career, family, finance,
health, social, and spiritual goals.
Next break down SMART goals.
Come up with a definite objective
and then break that objective down
into smaller attainable pieces.
Keep those goals SMART by ensuring
that they're specific, measurable, attainable,
realistic, and time-based.
Third, celebrate wins along the way.
Don't just focus on the reward at the finish line.
The next time you meet a milestone recognize that success,
feel proud, and allow yourself to indulge in a small reward
such as a trip to the movies or a night out with friends.
Fourth, don't compare yourself to others.
Comparisons only waste time
and paint an unrealistic picture of reality.
Instead look within.
Look at where you've been and how you've improved.
Only compare yourself to yourself.
And finally control your internal self-talk.
We all have an inner voice
that's constantly feeding us information,
some positive and some negative.
To maintain motivation control that self-talk
so that it acts as a coach rather than a critic.
Tell yourself my goals are possible.
The key to self-motivation is remembering
that it's up to you to determine what happens.
You are in control.
And if you feel like you're falling off track,
remember the tips we just covered.
Follow these strategies and you can bring
your goals to fruition.